我要问的下一个问题是
The next question, we're going to ask:
RSA真的是一个单向函数吗？
is RSA really an one-way function?
换句话说，在不知道陷门的情况下
In other words, is it really hard to
求RSA的逆真的有这么难吗？
invert RSA without knowing the trapdoor?
如果一个攻击者想求RSA函数的逆
So, if an attacker wanted to invert the RSA function,
攻击者有公钥
well, what the attacker has, is basically the public key,
即(N,e)。现在他有x^e
namely he has N and e. And now, he is given x to the e
他的目标是还原x。好，问题是
and his goal is to recover x. OK, so the question really is:
有了x^e mod N，还原x的难度有多大？
given x to the e modulo N, how hard is it to
我们真正问的是
recover x? So, what we're really asking is,
计算合数模的e次方根有多难？
how hard is it to compute e'th roots modulo a composite?
如果这个问题实际上很难，那么RSA事实上就是一个单向函数
If this problem turns out to be hard, then RSA is in fact an one-way function.
如果这个问题实际上是容易的
If this problem turns out to be easy, which
当然我们不相信它是容易的，那么RSA就会被破解了
of course we don't believe it's easy, then RSA would actually be broken.
实际上这个问题的目前的最好算法
So, it turns out the best algorithm for this problem
需要我们首先分解模N
requires us to first factor the modulus N.
然后，一旦我们分解了模，上周我们已经看过了
And then, once we factored the modulus, we have already
容易计算模p的e次方根
seen last week, that it's easy to compute the e'th root modulo p,
容易计算模q的e次方根
it's easy to compute the e'th root modulo q.
然后有了这些e次方根，实际上容易把它们组合起来
And, then given both those e'th roots, it's actually easy to combine them together,
使用所谓了中国剩余定理
using what's called the Chinese remainder theorem
既可以还原模N的e次方根
and actually recover the e'th root modulo N.
我们一旦能够分解模
So, once we are able to factor the modulus,
计算模N的e次方根就会很容易
computing e'th roots modulo N becomes easy.
但是分解模，就目前来看
But, factoring the modulus, as far as
是一个非常困难的问题
we know, is a very, very difficult problem.
但是一个自然的问题是，为了计算模N的e次方根
But a natural question is, is it true that in
我们真的一定要分解模N吗？
order to compute e'th roots modulo N, we have to
就目前我们所知道的
factor the modulus N? As far as we know, the
最好的计算模N的e次方根的算法
best algorithm for computing e'th roots
是需要将N因子分解的
modulo N requires factorization of N.
但谁知道呢，也许就有一条捷径呢
But, who knows, maybe there is a short cut
可以让我们计算模N的e次方根
that allows us to compute e'th roots modulo N,
而不用分解模
without factoring the modulus. To show that
为了证明这是不可能的，我们必须证明一个规约
that's not possible, we have to show a reduction.
就是说我们必须证明
That is, we have to show that,
如果我给大家一个有效算法
if I give you an efficient algorithm for
可以计算模N的e次方根
computing e'th roots modulo N, that
这个算法也可以被改造成一个计算因子分解的算法
efficient algorithm can be turned into a factoring algorithm.
这叫做一个规约。即有一个计算模N的e次方根的算法
So, this is called a reduction. Namely, given an algorithm for
我们就能获得一个分解合数的算法了
e'th roots modulo N, we obtain a factoring algorithm.
这会证明任何人都不能计算模N的e次方根
That would show that one cannot compute e'th roots modulo N
以比分解模更快的速度
faster than factoring the modulus.
如果我们有这么一个结果，这就会证明
If we had such a result, it would show that
破解RSA实际上与分解大合数一样难
actually breaking RSA, in fact is as hard as factoring.
但很不幸，目前这个证明我们还不知道
But, unfortunately, this is not really known at the moment.
事实上这是公钥密码学里最古老的问题之一
In fact, this is one of the oldest problems in public key crypto.
那么，我只给大家一个具体的例子
So, just let me give you a concrete example.
假设我给你一个算法，可以计算模N的立方根
Suppose, I give you an algorithm that will compute cube roots modulo N.
对任意Z_N中的x，这个算法会计算出x的模N立方根
So, for any x in ZN, the algorithm will compute the cube root of x modulo N.
我的问题是，你能证明，使用这样一个算法
My question is, can you show that using
你能分解模N吗？
such an algorithm you can factor the modulus N?
即使整个证明我们还不知道
And, even that is not known. What is known,
我会告诉你，我们知道的是，例如e=2时
I'll tell you, is for example that for e equals 2,
如果我给你一个计算模N平方根的算法
that is if I give you an algorithm for computing square roots modulo N,
那么事实上，这就蕴涵着分解模的算法
then in fact, that does imply factoring the modulus.
那么，计算平方根事实上与分解模一样困难
So, computing square roots is in fact as hard as factoring the modulus.
很不幸，如果你回想RSA的定义
Unfortunately, if you think back to the definition of RSA,
要求ed = 1 mod φ(N)
that required that e times d be 1 modulo phi(N).
这意味着，e与模φ(N)必须是互质的
What that means is, that e necessarily needs to be relatively prime to phi(N).
这里第一个方程是说，e是模φ(N)可逆的
Right, this, what the first equation says is that e is invertible modulo phi(N).
但是，如果e是φ(N)可逆的，这必将意味着
But, if e is invertible modulo phi(N), necessarily that means that
e必须与φ(N)互质
e must be relatively prime to phi(N).
但是如果大家记得，φ(N)=(p-1)(q-1)
But, phi(N), if you remember, that is equal to p minus 1 times q minus 1.
由于p和q都是大质数，p-1和q-1总是偶数
And, since p and q are both large primes,  p - 1 times q - 1 is always even.
因此gcd(2,φ(N))=2
And, as a result,  the GCD of 2 and phi(N) is equal to 2,
因为φ(N)是偶数，因此
because phi(N) is even. And therefore, the public
公钥指数2与φ(N)不互质
exponent 2 is not relatively prime to phi(N).
这意味着，即使我们有了一个从计算平方根
Which means that, even though we have a reduction
到因子分解的规约
from taking square roots to factoring,
e=2也不能被拿来当作RSA指数
e equals 2 cannot be used as an RSA exponent.
(容易看出，偶数都不能成为RSA指数)
那么真正合法的最小的RSA指数等于3
So, really the smallest RSA exponent that is legal is in fact e equals 3.
但是等于3，问题就是计算立方根
But, for e equal 3, the question of whether computing cube roots
与因子分解一样难，这是个开放问题
is as hard as factoring, is an open problem.
这个问题很有趣，值得想想
It's actually a lot of fun to think about this question.
那么我鼓励大家简单想想这个问题
So, I would encourage you to think about it just a little bit.
就是说，如果我给你一个有效算法，来计算模N的立方根
That is, if I give you an efficient algorithm for computing cube roots modulo N,
你能使用这个算法来分解模N吗？
can you use that algorithm to actually factor the modulus N?
我会告诉大家，有一些证据说明
I will tell you that there is a little bit of evidence to say
这样的规约可能并不存在，但这只是一个很弱的证据
that a reduction like that, actually doesn't exist, but it is very, very weak evidence.
这个证据是说
What this evidence says is basically, if you
如果你给我一个非常特别的形式的规约
give me a reduction of a very particular form.
换句话说，如果你的规约是代数的
In other words, if your reduction is what's called algebraic,
我这里先不解释它的意义
I am not going to explain what that means here.
如果有一个立方根神谕，你可以给我一个算法
That is, if given a cube root oracle, you could actually show me an algorithm
可以计算因子分解。这个规约本身
that would then factor. That reduction, by itself,
就会蕴涵着因子分解的算法
would actually imply a factoring algorithm.
这就是说，如果因子分解是困难的
Okay so, that would say that if factoring is hard,
那么规约根本就不存在
a reduction actually doesn't exist.
但是，如我所说，这是非常弱的证据
But, as I say this is very weak evidence.
因为，需要规约是代数的
Because, who is to say that the reduction needs to be algebraic.
也许会有其他类型的规约
Maybe, there are some other types of reductions that
比如我们没有考虑过的类型
we haven't really considered. So, I would
那么我会鼓励大家去略微考虑一下这个问题
encourage you to think a little bit about this
这是很有趣的
question. It's actually quite interesting.
如何使用一个立方根算法来分解模？
How would you use a cube root algorithm to factor the modulus?
但是如我所说，我们目前只知道RSA是一个单向函数
But as I said, as far as we know, RSA is a one way function.
事实上破解RSA，计算e次方根，都要求因子分解模
In fact, breaking RSA, computing e'th roots that is, actually requires factoring the modulus.
我们都相信那是正确的，这就是目前的研究现状
We all believe that's true, and that's the state of the art.
但是，现在有很多研究工作，试图提高RSA的性能
But, now there has been a lot of work on trying to improve the performance of RSA.
提高RSA加密的性能，或是RSA解密的性能
Either, RSA encryption or improve the performance of RSA decryption.
实际上，这个研究方向开始时人们走了很多弯路
And it turns out, there has been a number of false starts in this direction.
我想展示给大家这个非常好的例子，作为警示
So I want to show you, this wonderful example as a warning.
这是一个试图提高RSA性能的错误例子
So basically, this is an example of how not to improve the perfomance of RSA.
设想如果我想加速RSA解密
So, you might think that if I wanted to speed up RSA decryption,
记得解密是通过计算
remember decryption is done by raising the
密文的d次方。大家记得
ciphertext to the power of d. And, you remember
指数算法的运行时间
that the exponentiation algorithm ran in linear
与d的长度大小成线性关系，与log(d)成线性
time in the size of d. Linear time in log of d.
那么大家可以回想一下，如果我想
So, you might think to yourself, well if I wanted
加速RSA解密，我为什么不使用一个小d呢？
to speed up RSA decryption, why don't I just use a small d.
比如说，使用一个解密指数，大约是2的128次方
I'll say, I'll say a decryption exponent that's on the order of 2 to the 128.
那么这已经够大了，穷举d实际上是不可能的
So it's clearly big enough so that exhaustive search against d is not possible.
但正常情况下，解密指数d约与模一般大，比如说2000位
But normally, the decryption exponent d would be as big as the modulus, say 2000 bits.
通过使用仅为128位的d，我可以提高RSA解密速度20倍
By using d that's only 128 bits, I basically speed up RSA decryption by a factor of 20.
我从2000位降到100位
Right, I went down from 2000 bits to 100 bits.
那么计算指数的速度会快20倍
So, exponentiation would run 20 times as fast.
实际上这是一个糟糕的点子。
非常糟糕的点子，根据接下来的思路来看
It turns out this is a terrible idea. Terrible, terrible idea, in the following sense.
Michael Wiener有一个攻击，证明了事实上
There is an attack by Michael Wiener that shows that, in fact,
一旦私钥指数d小于模的4次方
as soon as the private exponent d is less than the fourth root of the modulus.
我们看，如果模大约是2048位
Let's see, if the modulus is around 2048 bits
这意味着如果d小于2的512次方，那么RSA是完全不安全的
that means that if d is less that 2 to the 512, then RSA is completely, completely insecure.
而且这是最坏的一种不安全
And, this is, it's insecure in the worst possible way.
即给定一个公钥e，你可以很快还原出私钥d
Namely, just given a public key and an e, you can very quickly recover the private key d.
所以有传言说：这个攻击可以针对最多512位
Well, so some folks said: well this attack works up to 512 bits.
那么为什么我们不让这个模，比如说530位
So, why don′t we make the modulus, say, you know 530 bits.
那么这个攻击就不能用了
Then, this attack actually wouldn't apply.
但是我们依然可以让RSA解密加速4倍
But still, we get to speed up RSA decryption by a factor of 4,
因为我们把指数从2000位降到比如说530位
because we shrunk the exponent from 2000 bits to, say, 530 bits.
实际上，即使这是不安全的。事实上
Well it turns out, even that is not secure. In fact,
Wiener的攻击有一个扩展
there is an extension to Wiener's attack, that's actually much
复杂得多的扩展，证实了
more complicated, that shows that if d
如果d小于N^0.292，那么RSA也是不安全的
is less than N to the 0.292, then also RSA is insecure.
事实上，这个猜想是说，这对最多N^0.5来说是正确的
And in fact, the conjecture that this is true up to N to the 0.5.
即使d大约为N^0.4999，RSA依然是不安全的
So even if d is like N to the 0.4999, RSA should still be insecure,
尽管这是个开放问题，也是一个极好的开放问题
although this is an open problem. It's again, a wonderful open problem,
这个问题已经14年未解决了
It's been open for like, what is it, 14 years now.
没人可以超过这个0.292
And, nobody can progress beyond this 0.292.
这有点奇怪
Somehow, it seems kind of strange, why would 0.292
为什么0.292会是正确答案，没人能超过0.292呢？
be the right answer and yet no one can go beyond 0.292.
那么为了准确，当我说RSA是不安全时
So, just to be precise, when I say that RSA is insecure,
我的意思是，有了公钥(N,e)
what I mean is just given the public key N and e,
你的目标是还原私钥d
your goal is to recover the secret key d.
如果你好奇0.292是怎么来的
If you are curious where 0.292 comes from,
我会告诉你，它实际上是1-1/√2
I'll tell you that what it is, it's basically 1 minus 1 over square root of 2.
为什么这会是问题的正确答案呢？
Now how could this possibly be the right answer to this problem?
如果答案是N^0.5，会更自然得多
It's much more natural that the answer is N to the 0.5.
但这依然是一个开放问题。如果你想思考一下
But this is still an open problem. Again if you want to think about that,
这是一个很有趣的问题，值得研究
it's kind of a fun problem to work on.
这里的教训是，任何人都不应该在d上强加任何结构
So the lesson in this is that one should not enforce any structure on d
以期提高RSA性能，事实上
for improving the performance of RSA, and in fact
现在有很多这样的结果，证实了
now there's a slew of results like this that show
任何像这样的试图提高RSA性能的技巧
that basically, any kind of tricks like this to try and improve RSA's performance
最后都会带来灾难。这不是正确的提高RSA性能的方法
is going to end up in disaster. So this is not the right way to improve RSA's performance.
我本不想讲解Wiener攻击的细节
Initially I wasn't going to cover the details of Wiener's attack.
但是根据课堂上的讨论情况，我觉得有人很想看这些细节
But given the discussions in the class, I think some of you would enjoy seeing the details.
它涉及的只是操作一些不等式
All it involves is just manipulating some inequalities.
如果你对这个很不舒服，大可跳过这一张幻灯片
If you're not comfortable with that, feel free to skip over this slide,
尽管我想有很多人很想看这些细节
although I think many of you would actually enjoy seeing the details.
那么我提醒大家，在Wiener的攻击里
So let me remind you in Wiener's attack basically
我们有模和RSA指数：(N,e)
we're given the modulus and the RSA exponent N and e,
我们的目标是还原d，私钥指数d
and our goal is to recover d, the private exponent d,
我们只知道d是小于N的四次方根的
and all we know is that d is basically less than the fourth root of N.
事实上我将假设d小于N的四次方根再除以3
In fact, I'm going to assume that d is less than the fourth root of N divided by 3.
这个3不重要，但这里主要起作用的项是，d小于N的4次方根
This 3 doesn't really matter, but the dominating term here is that d is less than the 4th root of N.
我们来看怎么办。首先记得
So let's see how to do it. So first of all, recall that
因为e和d是RSA的公钥和私钥指数
because e and d are RSA public and private exponents,
我们知道ed = 1 mod φ(N)。这是什么意思？
we know that e times d is 1 modulo phi(N). Well what does that mean?
这意味着，存在某个整数k，满足ed = kφ(N)+1
That means that there exists some integer k such that e times d is equal to k times phi(N) plus 1.
这也就是ed = 1 mod φ(N)的含义
Basically that's what it means for e times d to be 1 modulo phi(N).
也就是某个整数乘以φ(N)再加1
Basically some integer multiple of phi(N) plus 1.
那么现在我们盯着这个等式看一会
So now let's stare at this equation a little bit.
事实上这个等式是这个攻击的关键所在
And in fact this equation is the key equation in the attack.
首先我们将两边同时除以d*φ(N)
And what we're going to do is first of all divide both sides by d times phi(N).
事实上我把这项移到左边
And in fact I'm going to move this term here to the left.
在我两边同除以d*φ(N)后，得到
So after I divide by d times phi(N), what I get is that
e/φ(N)-k/d=1/(d*φ(N))
e divided by phi(N) minus k divided by d is equal to 1 over d times phi(N).
那么我只是除以d*φ(N)
Okay, so all I did is I just divided by d times phi(N)
然后把k*φ(N)这一项移到等式左边
and I moved the k times phi(N) term to the left-hand side.
现在为了说的清楚点，我要加上绝对值
Now, just for the heck of it I'm going to add absolute values here.
这一步待会会有用，但是它们当然不会改变等性
These will become useful in just a minute, but of course they don't change this equality at all.
现在φ(N)当然几乎等于N，φ(N)与N非常接近，我们之前说过
Now, phi(N) of course is almost N; phi(N) is very, very close to N, as we said earlier.
现在我需要它们，对于这个分式
And all I'm going to need then for this fraction is just to say that
我说它小于1/√N，它比1/√N小得多
it's less than 1 over square root of N. It's actually much, much smaller
因为1/φ(N)是在1/N数量级的
than 1 over square root of N, it's actually on the order of 1 over N or even more than that,
但为了我们的目的，我只需要这个分式小于1/√N
but for our purposes all we need is that this fraction is less than 1 over square root of N.
现在我们盯着这个分式看一会
Now let's stare at this fraction for just a minute.
大家发现左边的分式我们并不知道
You realize that this fraction on the left here is a fraction that we don't actually know.
我们知道e，但我们不知道φ(N)，因此我们不知道e/φ(N)
We know e, but we don't know phi(N), and as a result we don't know e over phi(N).
但我们对e/φ(N)有一个良好的估计
But we have a good approximation to e over phi(N). Namely we know that phi(N)
现在我们知道φ(N)与N非常近。因此e/φ(N)与e/N很近
is very close to N. Therefore e over phi(N) is very close to e over N.
那么我们对左边的e/N有了一个很好的估计
So we have a good approximation to this left-hand side fraction, namely e over N.
我们想要的是右边的分式
What we really want is the right-hand side fraction,
因为一旦我们有了右边的分式
because once we get the right-hand side fraction,
它涉及d，那么我们就可以还原d了
basically that's going to involve d, and then we'll be able to recover d. Okay, so let's see
我们看，如果我们把e/φ(N)换成e/N，看看我们会获得何种错误
if we replace e over phi(N) by e over N, let's see what kind of error we're going to get.
分析一下，我们首先提醒自己
So to analyze that, what we'll do is first of all remind ourselves
φ(N)实际上是N-p-q+1
that phi(N) is basically N - p - q + 1,
意味着N-φ(N)=p+q-1<p+q
which means that N minus phi(N) is going to be less than p + q.
更精确地，我应该写p+q+1，但大家知道
Actually I should, to be precise I should really write p + q + 1, but you know,
没人关系这个1，它不会有任何影响
who cares about this 1, it's not, it doesn't really affect anything.
为了简单，我要忽略它
So I'm just going to ignore it for simplicity.
好，那么N-φ(N)<p+q，p和q大约是N长度的一半
Okay, so N - phi(N) is less than p + q. Both p and q are roughly half the length of N,
大家知道，它们是N的平方根的数量级
so you know, they're both kind of on the order of square root of N,
所以我们说p+q<3√N
so basically p + q we'll say is less than 3 times square root of N.
好，我们待会使用这个不等式
Okay, so we're going to use this inequality in just a minute.
但现在我们开始使用这个关于d的事实
But now we're going to start using the fact that we know something about d,
即d是小的，如果我们看这个不等式
namely that d is small. So if we look at this inequality here,
d是小于N的四次方根除以3
d is less than the fourth root of N divided by 3.
容易看出如果我们两边平方
It's actually fairly easy to see that if I square both sides
稍微做点操作，就不难看出
and I just manipulate things a little bit, it's [not] difficult to see that
这直接能导出下面的关系
this directly implies the following relation,
(1/2d^2)-1/√N>3/√N
basically 1 over 2 d squared minus 1 over square root of N is greater than 3 over square root of N.
如我所说，这是由两边平方得来的
As I said, this basically follows by squaring both sides, then taking the
平方后再取倒数，然后我猜一边还要乘以0.5
inverse of both sides, and then I guess multiplying one side by a half.
好，那么大家可以很容易推出这个关系，
我们待会要用这个关系
Okay, so you can easily derive this relation, and we'll need this relation in just a minute.
现在我们看，我们要界定
So now let's see, what we'd like to do is bound
e/N与k/d之间的距离，我们知道什么？
the difference of e over N and k over d. Well what do we know?
根据三角不等式，我们知道这个
By the triangular inequality, we know that this is equal to
不大于|e/N-e/φ(N)|
the distance between e over N and e over phi(N) plus
加上|e/φ(N)-k/d|
the distance from e over phi(N) to k over d.
这就是三角不等式，是绝对值的一个性质
This is just what's called a triangular inequality; this is just a property of absolute values.
现在我们知道如何界定这个绝对值
Now this absolute value here, we already know how to bound.
想一下，这是我们刚刚推出来的界
If you think about it it's basically the bound that we've already derived.
那么我们知道这个绝对值是小于1/√N
So we know that this absolute value here is basically less than 1 over square root of N.
现在关于这个绝对值，我们知道什么？e/N-e/φ(N)是什么？
Now what do we know about this absolute value here? What is e over N minus e over phi(N)?
我们计算公分母，看看我们能得到什么
Well let's do common denominators and see what we get.
公分母是N乘以φ(N)
So the common denominator is going to be N times phi(N),
这里的分组将是e*(φ(N)-N)
and the numerator in this case is going to be e times phi(N) minus N.
从这个等式，我们知道它小于3√N
Which we know from this expression here is less than 3 times square root of N.
这个分子将是e*(3)
So really what this numerator is going to be is e times 3 square root of N.
分子将小于e(3√N)
The numerator is going to be less than e times 3 square root of N.
那么我知道，e<φ(N)，于是e/φ(N)<1
So now I know that e is less than phi(N), so I know that e over phi(N) is less than 1.
换句话说，如果我擦去e和φ(N)，只会让这个分式变大
In other words, if I erase e and I erase phi(N) I've only made the fraction larger.
那么这个最初的绝对值现在将是
Okay, so this initial absolute value is now going to be
小于(3√N)/N
smaller than 3 square root of N over N, which is simply,
(3√N)/N也就是3/√N
3 square root of N over N is simply 3 over square root of N.
但是关于3/√N，我们知道什么？
Okay, but what do we know about 3 over square root of N?
我们知道它小于1/(2d^2)-1/√N
We know that it's less than 1 over 2 d squared minus 1 over square root of N.
好，我们的推导结束了
Okay, so that's the end of our derivation.
那么现在第一个绝对值是小于1/(2d^2)-1/√N
So now we know that the first absolute value is less than 1 over 2 d squared minus square root of N.
第二个绝对值小于1/√N
The second absolute value is less than 1 over square root of N.
因此它们的和是小于1/(2d^2)的
And therefore their sum is less than 1 over 2 d squared.
我想让大家盯着这个表达式看
And this is the expression that I want you to stare at.
那么这里，让我把它给圈出来。我来把这部分和这部分圈出来
So here, let me circle it a little bit. So let me circle this part and this part.
现在，我们盯着这个分式看一会
Now, so let's stare a little bit at this fraction here.
我们看到，首先与前面一样，现在我们知道了e/N的值
And what we see is first of all, as before, now we know the value of e over N,
我们想知道k/d的值
and what we'd like to find out is the value k over d.
关于这个分式k/d，我们知道什么？
But what do we know about this fraction k over d?
我们知道这两个分式的差非常小
We know somehow that the difference of these two fractions is really small;
它小于1/(2d^2)。现在实际上这个很少发生
it's less than 1 over 2 d squared. Now this turns out to happen very infrequently,
k/d如此好地逼近e/N
that k over d approximates e over N so well that
以至于两者之间的差比k/d的分母平方还小
the difference between the two is less than the square of the denominator of k over d.
这个实际上不是经常发生
It turns out that that can't happen very often.
实际上很少有具有k/d形式的分式，能够如此好地逼近另一分式
It turns out that there are very few fractions of the form k over d that approximate another fraction
以至于它们的差小于1/(2d^2)
so well that their difference is less than 1 over 2 d squared.
事实上，这样的分式最多也只有log(N)那么多
And in fact the number of such fractions is going to be at most logarithmic in N.
现在有一个连分式算法，这是一个著名的连分式算法
So now there's a continued fraction algorithm. It's a very famous fraction
它会从分式e/N开始
that basically what it will do is, from the fraction e over N,
他会还原log(N)个可能的k/d的值
it will recover log(N) possible candidates for k over d.
我们只需要一个一个地去试，知道我们找到正确的k/d
So we just try them all one by one until we find the correct k over d.
然后就结束了，因为我们知道了
And then we're done. We're done, because we know that,
ed = 1 mod k，因此d与k互质
well e times d is 1 mod k, therefore d is relatively prime to k,
那么如果我们用一个有理分式来表示k/d，也就是分子除以分母
so if we just represent k over d as a rational fraction, you know, numerator by denominator,
分母一定是d，那么我们就还原了
the denominator must be d. And so we've just recovered, you know,
我们已经试了所有可能的log(N)个分式，它们很好地逼近了e/N
we've tried all possible log(N) fractions that approximate e over N so well
使得它们的差小于1/(2d^2)
that the difference is less than 1 over 2 d squared.
然后我们只看所有这些分式的分母，其中一个分母必定是d
And then we just look at the denominator of all those fractions, and one of those denominators must be d.
那么我们讲完了。我们已经还原了私钥
And then we're done; we've just recovered the private key.
这是一个很犀利的攻击，它展示了
So this is a pretty acute attack. And it shows basically how,
如果私钥太小，小于N的四次方根的话
if the private exponent is small, smaller than the fourth root of N,
那么我们可以轻松地完全还原d。那我就讲到这
then we can recover d completely, quite easily. Okay, so I'll stop here.